welcome back to 25 minute physiology
right try to demystify and simplify
science to help you reach your Fitness
performance and training goals now
today's topic I want to talk about fat
carbohydrates fat loss and performance
the reason I'm doing this is because I
would had the pleasure of being on Joe
Rogan's podcast yesterday and this topic
came up a little bit but I I kicked
myself as I left because we didn't
really clarify the situation sometimes I
forget how important and necessary it is
for us to go back to the very beginning
lay the foundation so that we really
understand what we're talking about if
you promise to give me these next 20 or
so minutes I guarantee you you'll leave
with more clarity about what carbs are
and what fat are are they bad for you
are they good than you've ever had
before I know that's a bold statement
but we think we can get there so let's
start the very very Basics and that's
how fat loss occurs right well what most
of us don't really realize is it's very
simple it's simply through breathing you
can go check out my 55 minute physiology
of fat loss video if you want more
information but basically what happens
is you inhale
oxygen you exhale carbon
dioxide the difference is of course
carbon where that carbon comes from is
your own internal body what most folks
don't realize is your fat is a long
chain of carbon so here's what happens
you do something like exercise and you
create a demand or a need for
energy the way you generate cellular
energy is to break molecular bonds so if
your fat is a long chain of carbons that
are put together with chemical bonds and
you come along and you break one of
those
bonds like that that released energy in
this particular case it's a net positive
resultant energy you use that energy to
then power the
excise but you've got a free floating
carbon that is now
wasted in order to process that you take
a Big Gulp of air
in breathe in oxygen combine that with
that free floating carbon to make carbon
dioxide then
exhale and rid yourself of that carbon
dioxide now since your fat was a long
chain of carbon and you broke one of
those carbons off and it's now gone back
to the atmosphere as waste the length of
your carbon chain got shorter and
shorter and shorter this is literally
how you lose
fat now plants are a little bit the
opposite so a plant breathes in
CO2 and breathes out
O2 they used light as their energy
source because they don't have the
ability to make energy like we do or
well to be more honest we don't have the
ability to make energy the way they do
but they use a process called photo
synthesis so they bring in carbon
dioxide of course add water and that
light is used to power the synthesis
process of putting together carbon
dioxide molecules
so really they're going the exact
opposite of what we do we breathe in O2
breathe out CO2 to get rid of our stored
carbon they are breathing in CO2 so that
they can
extract that carbon and get rid of the
oxygen back into the
atmosphere Well turns out a
carbohydrate is simply a
carbon that has been added to a water
molecule or that has been hydrated
so the basic molecular structure of a
carbohydrate is a chain of
carbons sound
familiar 1 2 3 4 five six
carbons six carbons attached to six
water
molecules right so C6
h126 that in particular is the structure
of what's called glucose or fructose
now those are two of your three
monosaccharides so a simple
sugar is one of those sugar molecules
the third one of course is
galactose now when a plant does that
breathe in CO2 breathe out O2 thing
they're making either glucose or
fructose simple sugars if you combine
two or more monosaccharides so in this
case it wouldn't matter if it's two
glucose or one glucose one fructose or
two fructose or one glucose one
galactose doesn't matter but anytime you
put two monosaccharides together you get
what's called a
disaccharide now in the case of plants
what they're usually doing is forming
initially either glucose or fructose
they combine those together and that's
what we call sucrose so it's a
disaccharide with one fructose one
glucose and the reason they do that is
because glucose is extremely
metabolically sensitive or active in
plants and humans in other words if a
cell finds glucose it's going to use it
for metabolism so plants have a problem
when they need to transport glucose back
or back and forth throughout its own
body system or it's its body because if
it puts too much glucose in the system
it's going to get absorbed up and it
won't get to its Target a great example
is how we make fruit so a plant will go
through this process generate glucose
and
fructose it'll combine them together to
make
sucrose put that in its little
bloodstream if you will send it around
to say the fruit part of the
plant break it back down into glucose
and
fructose the fructose stays along stays
around and the glucose then either goes
gets burned as metabolism or gets stored
as starch this is why fruits are
actually full of
fructose but things like potatoes or
root vegetables are more like starch
because they never go through this
fructose process also why the longer a
fruit sits and the longer it goes the
riper it gets because the more fructose
is converted and fructose is like five
to six times sweeter than
glucose all right for a variety reasons
now when it does this process it can it
gets left with its glucose so it's
fructose we then come along and say okay
we don't have this magical ability
to
generate or synthesize carbons into a
carbohydrate using light as a power so
what we have to do to make up for that
is we have to
then
consume these
Foods all right so we still inhale our
oxygen we ingest water we eat fructose
and starches to get our carbohydrate and
that's how we power our EX signes we
then
exhale carbon dioxide as our waste
product which funny
enough goes back in the
atmosphere and is of course reabsorbed
by the plant this is our magic circle of
life
right so we're just continuing to shift
carbon back and forth and moving it
around from the plant to U and plant and
back now that we understand the basics
let's move over to
application right now a lot of people
have heard carbohydrates but there's
real confusion about are they good for
me are they bad for me but wait Sugar's
bad for me but carbs are good or no wait
is it the opposite what are starch I
don't know so here are the basics of
what carbohydrates
mean most of the time this is split into
three categories there's some other
carbs but this is what we're going to
focus on now most of the time when we
say sugar what we're referring to is one
of these
monosaccharides right a simple sugar is
also almost synonymous with a
monosaccharide and it's simple because
it's easy to metabolize so if you were
to put a straight shot of simple sugar
in you or in a plant it gets metabolized
very quickly remember this is the reason
we had to make soup gross or the plant
has to do
it the downside of it
though is it can't be moved
around
so when we ingest our sugar or
monosaccharide or our simple sugar what
people tend to say is actually starch is
better for
you because it takes a lot longer to
break down what we have to understand is
it's not a good or a bad right there's
pros and cons to both approaches but
that's basically what a starch is which
is our second type of carbohydrate it is
a bunch of monosaccharides that have
been packed together really densely but
because they've been smashed together
they don't break down as fast they're
actually released slower into your
bloodstream so if you have a Bolis of
sugar or a Bolis of starch the sugar may
make your blood Spike really fast and
crash back down but the starch may be
really slowly because it takes a lot
time lot longer to break down now there
are times when you want both are times
when the other is not effective we'll
have to discuss that in a later video
the third aspect or type of
carbohydrates rather is fiber right so
we'll have to do this in another video
as well but this is an important
consideration so when we talk about
things like sucrose or sucrose or table
sugar one of the problems is we in not
that sugar is bad for us it doesn't hurt
us or kill us but when we ingest table
sugar or added sugars or processed
sugars by the way fun fact I wasn't
planning on going here but just so you
know uh most sugar comes from beets or
canes and it's brown and when they
refine it all the way down it turns
white because the dark color is actually
masses so they can use the Molasses then
and sell you the Molasses or they can
distill that down and make brown sugar
out of it that's what those are anyways
when we ingest a bunch of added table
sugar it's not necessarily a problem but
it it it comes in the form of a comes in
a non-natural form which is to say you
ingest a lot of sugar but you don't get
the fiber that's typically in Plants you
also don't get any of the other vitamins
and minerals or antioxidants that come
with the
fruit in addition we can also consume it
at a super high concentration that we
would never actually ingest it in in the
plant form
so it's not that it's bad for us but it
can lead to problems because of
concentration issues and because it
costs us important fiber and important
vitamins and
minerals starch on the other hand is
generally not distill down and and put
into packages and so the most of the
time when we consume starch it's coming
in the form of a plant or vegetable
which is generally why people say
starches are better for
you all right but that's not necessarily
true so now that we understand what's
going on here let's complete our final
picture
when you ingest that carbon then the
whole point was for you to store it
right but but it gets stored in a couple
of different
ways now carbon regardless of where it
really came from but we'll stick with
carbohydrates first is stored in one of
three
places it's stored in your blood as
blood sugar right so glucose and blood
sugar are really the same thing it's
stored in your muscle or your liver as
glycogen
now fun fact here just like a plant
stored its glucose as starch a human
stores its glucose as glycogen so muscle
glycogen and starch is really the same
thing depending on what animal it's in
or what planet's
in but that's where we store it now any
excess glucose or carbohydrate beyond
what we need to have in our blood or
beyond what we need in our liver or our
muscle is then of course stored as extra
fat and if we remember the chemical
structure of glucose or sugar being one
two three four five six carbon molecules
with six water if we look at fat we see
see it's very very similar so the stored
form of fat is typically a tri glyceride
which is one two three Tri glycerol so
it is a glycerol backbone which is this
three carbon chain glycerol meaning like
like glycogen and and glucose and all
those other sugars
one two three with three big long carbon
chains now the length of this carbon
chain instead of being six carbons like
glucose it could be 12 16 18 maybe even
more right the length of the carbon
chain determines what we call it and
these folks are fatty acids if you've
heard those things so medium chain short
chain long chain fatty acids Etc if it's
say 16 carbons we give it a certain name
if it's 17 carbons we call it a
different type of fatty acid and Etc by
the way there's actually some double
bonds going on here and if there's a
single bond that a break it say the
third chain we call that an omega-3
fatty acid if that break happens at the
six carbon we call that Omega 6 etc etc
just some fun stuff for another video
maybe but my point
is it's still a big chain of long chain
of carbons so the ability chemically for
us to convert from this type of chain of
carbon
to this chain of
carbon is actually fairly easy we have
to stop thinking about fat and carbs is
two things that are competing and
they're against each other they're
complimentary because of this how much
glucose can I possibly store in my
muscle well not very much relative to
how much fat I can
store right my muscle is only so big so
my body's going to want to keep glycogen
full in those areas but the fat is the
backup system so the analogy I like to
give is actually think of two gears on a
bicycle when one turns it helps the
other one turn now in some situations
you might want the front gear to be a
lot bigger than the back one and some
other situations it might be the inverse
sometimes they're equal that's sport
specificity right but the point is we
don't want to compromise either one of
them you would never want to be like I
cut that back gear completely off and
that's one of the problems when we focus
too much on going to one end or the
other end of this metabolic Spectrum
right which is another way of saying if
you force yourself so that you're an
optimal fat burner that could come at
the compromise of being able to burn
carbohydrates and vice versa now most of
us are probably not very good at burning
fat relative to carbohydrate so it's
maybe okay to emphasize improving your
fat burning abilities but nonetheless we
want to have this wonderful term that
wish I coined but I didn't called
metabolic
flexibility especially for someone who's
just interested in long-term health or a
variety of physical activity or exercise
sport performance Endeavors being able
to use fat when it's appropriate and
carbs when it's appropriate is far
better than optimizing one over the
other most of the time and that's
because of
this when you burn muscle glycogen or
use sugar as a
fuel two things number one it's coming
from the muscle itself self that's being
exercised so if you're doing a lot of
quadricep exercise for whatever reason
doing sprints or Hills or pushing a sled
or whatever you're burning the muscle
glycogen in that quadricep muscle
directly now the advantage is
carbohydrates are more metabolically
efficient per molecule of oxygen and
they're much faster because they're
right there the limitation of course is
again how many how much can we possibly
store my quad so after a few minutes or
seconds of Hard Exercise that number
starts going
down we then turn to fat and say okay
fat you're the backup system here the
advantage of fat is relative to the
amount of carbohydrates on my body I can
store way more fat but fat comes from
the entire body not from the exercising
muscle per
se so I burn all the muscle glycogen in
my quad but when I start using fat as a
fuel that fat has to come from the
entire body has to be broken down
mobilized put into blood uptaken into
the muscle uptaken into the St gone
through the mitochondria and finally
utilized for fuel so it's much slower so
both of these things have pros and cons
it's not one than the other we have to
get that mindset out of our head for the
vast majority of of things that we're
going to encounter outside of some
extreme circumstances we want to have
the ability to go back and forth between
them this is why we have the biology to
freaking do it right we wouldn't have it
if it wasn't potential benefit to it all
right so being able to go back and forth
is really really important we have a
advantages for both of
them so from a practical perspective
think of it this
way my body really cares about
maintaining the concentration of sugar
in my blood for variety of reasons and
it really cares about maintaining the
amount of glycogen in my muscle and my
liver right you always want that direct
quick supply of energy in case something
drastic happened you had to run escape
danger or something like that so if you
do something that depletes your muscle
glycogen your body's going to do
anything basically at at all costs to
replete it as fast as
possible but fat is really the backup
system right it doesn't really care the
amount of fat with the exception of it
getting very very very low I mean think
about this the vast majority of of us
have a very similar muscle glycogen
concentration but we have wild
differences in the amount of fat that we
store it's
backup so when you do a really hard B of
exercise uh really high-intensity
intervals maybe some heavy strength
training but you take a lot of volume
you burn that muscle glycogen well under
normal circumstances since this
conversion is so
easy you're going to actually convert
your fat you'll start breaking down your
fat to
replace your muscle
glycogen so in this case it doesn't
really particularly
matter if you're burning fat as your
fuel or carbs as your fuel during the
exercise in either case you will lose
your fat
so if we put this together hopefully the
wheels are turning in your head what's
the best type of exercise to then do if
you're interested in Fat
Loss well the obvious answer is it
doesn't particularly matter do the one
that you like the most do the one that
you're going to work the hardest at that
you'll do the most frequently that's
more important than anything advantages
of high-intensity exercise intervals
things like that hey they burn a lot of
muscle glycogen that's good for you
metabolically there's also advantage of
doing more of your traditional steady
state cardio so my general
recommendation is do both if you're just
the average person and you don't have a
maybe a goal or a competition in mind
maybe once a week do some steady state
cardio maybe once a week do some
intervals choose the bike choose the
airault bike or airine bike choose a
rower uh do circuit training go do hot
yoga anything you want do a combination
of things because all of it is going to
result in you doing what
it gets you to ventilate more right all
you're really doing with all this stuff
is tricking yourself into burning more
energy that's all you're trying to do so
don't get bogged down in the details of
the intensity the exercise do a
combination of
them now from the diet
perspective what's better
then high carb low fat low carb high fat
again I won't say that it doesn't matter
at
all but it doesn't matter in a lot of
cases if you're 60% fat or carbs or 40
or 30 as long as your total
carbon
intake is lower than the carbons you're
exhaling you're going to lose fat and if
you do this with good nutrition
vegetables plants animals good fats
proteins things like this you should be
able to lose fat while not losing too
much muscle mass be careful of fat loss
schemes that don't pay attention or tell
you about what happens to muscle mass
right so some poor nutrition plans may
help you lose fat but you'll also lose a
lot of muscle and that's not beneficial
either so any standard routine it
doesn't particularly matter if you want
to go low carb fine right make sure
though that you're not doing low
vegetable because then you won't get all
the vitamins and minerals and nutrients
or you won't have all the fiber this is
a major problem with those that go on
low carbohydrate diets especially if
they're cutting on other fruits and
vegetables so be careful of that it
could be done but just be careful if you
want to go on a high uh carbohydrate or
moderate carbohydrate diet hey that's
fine too your body's not that precious
it doesn't care that much there's a lot
of other implications to these diets but
for General Health for General
performance and fitness you have a lot
more flexibility and plasticity between
these two than most people want to
acknowledge so I hope that helped clear
some clear up some confusion I'm sure
I'll do many more videos uh on the
topics or others if you have any
suggestions of where you'd like me to go
please feel free to comment if not I get
this question a lot but this video or
any of the videos I post on my website
you're absolutely welcome to use them
for your own purposes uh if you I get a
lot of professors that want to use these
for class please do so of course I
appreciate you just crediting me back
and not stealing them and taking them on
your own but I make these so that you
share the information that's what's
important if you like this video you can
check out more of them on my website um
you can see them up on YouTube they're
around those of you that listen to the
RO the episode with Joe Rogan I hope
this helped clarify I'll send this to
him and see if uh he'll watch it and
maybe I'll have him back on and and
we'll cover in more detail but for now
again thank you all for your support and
uh we'll catch you next time